Inventory of the Herbert Oliver Brayer papers, 1803-1953 (Bulk 1871-1953)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Herbert Oliver Brayer papers
1803-1953
(bulk 1871-1953)
Brayer, Herbert Oliver
00079
2.45 cubic feet (3 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Biography of Herbert Oliver Brayer
Herbert Oliver Brayer (1913-) was an American historian during the twentieth century. An expert on the economic history of the American West, Brayer was born in Montreal, Canada and educated at the University of Southern California and the University of New Mexico. He served as Director of the Western Range Cattle Industry Study (1944-1949) and authored a number of books concerning the economic history of the American West, including "William Blackmore, A Case Study in the Economic Development of the West" (1949).
Scope and Content
Collection contains Herbert Oliver Brayer's research files, including those concerning the Western Range Cattle Industry Study, economic history of the American West, and "William Blackmore, A Case Study in the Economic Development of the West" (which contain correspondence, manuscripts, clippings, notes, legal documents, photographs, photograph negatives, and soundscriber disks). Collection also contains Brayer's personal correspondence, speech and book review manuscripts, notes, and biographical material. Two unidentified reel to reel audio tapes, miscellaneous clippings, and class materials are in this collection as well.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are two other known Herbert Oliver Brayer Collections preserved at the Colorado Historical Society Library and the Stanford University Department of Special Collections.
Acquisition Information
The collection was received from Herbert Oliver Brayer in 1948.
Access Terms
Blackmore, William, 1827-1878.; Western Range Cattle Industry Study.; Cattle trade -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century.; Ranching -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century.; Rangelands -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century.; Economic development -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century.; Ranchers -- West (U.S.) -- 19th century.; West (U.S.) -- Economic conditions -- 19th century.; West (U.S.) -- History -- 1860-1890.; West (U.S.) -- History -- 1890-1945.; Photographs.
Agriculture and Natural Resources; Ranching; Economics and Banking; Arts, Humanities, and Social Sciences; Education
Container List
- Series I. Personal
  - Biography of Herbert Oliver Brayer, 1932-1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from C. Barclay, Nottingham, 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Letter of Herbert O. Brayer regarding occupied Germany, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Report of Herbert Brayer on USIS, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Committee on Research in Economic History, Author H. Cole, 1942-1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Fred W. Hesse, 1949-1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Keystone View Co., 1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-North Dakota State Historical Society, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Recordak Co., 1946 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Rockefeller Foundation, David Stevens, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with W. Eugene Shiels of Xavier U. Cincinnati, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Brayer and Henry Swan of Swan Bros. L7 Ranch, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Henry Swan, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence- George Tait, U.S. Embassy in London, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-U.S. Army and Navy Departments. National Archives, 1941-1946 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-Westerners Denver Posse, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-A.A. Smith to Herbert Brayer, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Herbert O. Brayer in Soundscriber discs, 1945-1949 (Box 1)
  - Inventory of Historical Societies, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Inventory of L.A. Huffman photographs, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts of book reviews by Herbert O. Brayer, 1943-1948 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Cartoons, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 1)
  - Outlines for Courses in American Economic History, 1945-1948 (Box 1)
  - Programs and book promotional material, 1941-1949 (Box 1)
  - Soundscriber-Brayer's Introduction to Brand Book, undated (Box 1)
  - Soundscriber dics made in England, 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Soundscriber practice disk, undated (Box 1)
  - Radio broadcast transcript-"Observation Post" Number 2 England, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Speech on post World War II Communism, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Speech on Latin America, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Notes on Speech, untitled, on railroads, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Speech "A Catholic Approach to Latin America", 1942 (Box 1)
  - Speech "A British Influence on Western Range Cattle Industry", 1948 (Box 1)
  - Speech "Crisis and Understanding", 1946 (Box 1)
  - Speeches by Brayer "The Good Neighbor Policy At Home", 1945 (Box 1)
  - Speech "A Letter to Joe About Colorado", Kiwanis Club, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Travel Receipts, miscellaneous notes, etc, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Travel Receipts, miscellaneous notes, etc, 1945 (Box 1)
  - William Henry Jackson Obituaries, 1942 (Box 1)
- Series II. Western History
  - Edinburg Monthly Stock and Share List, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clipping, March 16, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Yellowstone Park-Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts-Mormon Cattle Drive, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Transcipt-Indian Fighting, from Saratoga Sun, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-Mormons "Life of R.L. Praetor Reveals Interesting Historical Facts", 1939 (Box 1)
  - Transcripts-John W. "Josh" Deane from Cody Enterprise, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"Frank Brigham and Basin in 1898", 1937 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"The Uinta Stock Farm and the Beckwith Race Tracks", 1897 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-Indians near Saratoga, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"Cokeville, Wyoming: Livest of Them All", 1917 (Box 1)
  - Transcripts-Sam Moses, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"Old Timer" (Oliver Perry Hanna), 1934 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-Boney Earnest, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-Reminiscenses of R.M. Galbraith, 1922 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"The Battle of Beartown", undated (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"A Bit of Unwritten History", 1928 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"The Story of Jack Watkins", undated (Box 1)
  - "Dayton, the Historical", 1940 (Box 1)
  - Transcipt-"Piedmont Wyoming", 1940 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-Republican Boomerang, June 30, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-David Charles Cummings, undated (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"Last of Bonanza, Frontier Town Wiped Out", 1939 (Box 1)
  - Transcript from the Autobiography of A.A. Anderson, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Transcripts-Livestock and Agriculture in the Bighorn Basin, 1937-1939 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-Frank Blackburn, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"The Oldest National Forest", 1936 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-Winter of 1886-87, 1886-1887 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"Mrs. Elizabeth Tallman Describes Perils of Early Days in Denver", 1927-1931 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-Ascent of Grand Teton, 1899 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript-"Boom Town Banker Central City Colorado" by Herbert Brayer, 1880 (Box 1)
  - Maps-William Blackmore, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, Maps-William Blackmore, 1870 (Box 1)
  - Photographs-William Blackmore, 1870 (Box 1)
  - Photography by W. H. Jackson, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Notes for book publication-William Blackmore, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Biographical-William Blackmore, 1878 (Box 1)
  - Ledger-Brown Bros., 1861-1875 (Box 1)
  - Transcript-"William Blackmore" from Western Entreprenuer, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Lee Hawk-"Jesse James", February-March 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Lee Hawk-"Jesse James", December 1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Lee Hawk-"Jesse James", 1948-1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Lee Hawk-"Jesse James", January 1952, January 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Lee Hawk-"Jesse James", January 1953-February 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Lee Hawk-"Jesse James", October 1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Lee Hawk-"Jesse James", December 1952-March 1953 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Lee Hawk-"Jesse James", November-December 1952 (Box 1)
  - Lee Hawk letter and photos, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Photographs-Dude Ranches, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs-By W. H. Jackson, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Photographs-"Indians"(Members of the Navajo, Apache, and Pueblo Tribes), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Sacajawea, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Notes from books and newspapers-Francis Schlatter, 1895-1947 (Box 1)
  - Photographs-Francis Schlatter, 1895 (Box 1)
  - Photograph Negatives-Francis Schlatter, 1895 (Box 1)
  - Photographs and Negatives-Joseph Addison Thatcher, undated (Box 1)
  - Penitentes of New Mexico, 1915 (Box 2)
  - Gallina, New Mexico, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Land Grants- Letter of George Gold, 1855 (Box 2)
  - Photographs-Land Grants and Ute Indians, 1875-1878 (Box 2)
  - Land Grants-New Mexico Records available,list, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Land Grants-document in spanish, 1803 (Box 2)
  - Land Grants-Opinion on the Matter of the Las Animas, 1880 (Box 2)
  - Land Grants-Proposal by John Collinson, 1874 (Box 2)
  - Land Grants-photograph of a sketch of Ceran St. Vrain, undated (Box 2)
- Series III. Western Range Cattle Industry
  - Documents-Bureau of Animal Industry Report, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Documents-Bureau of Animal Industry Report for 1886 (incomplete), 1887 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of Sidford Hamp, 1872 (Box 2)
  - Foreward to Jeff Dillard's diary, 1896 (Box 2)
  - Manuscript-Autobiography of Edward Swan, undated (Box 2)
  - Manuscript on Moreton Frewen, undated (Box 2)
  - Transcript-Memoirs of "Kansas" Wickwire, 1935 (Box 2)
  - "British Influence in..." (by Herbert Brayer), 1948 (Box 2)
  - Map-Jack Potter's Map of Cattle Trails, 1895 (Box 2)
  - Documents-Bureau of Animal Industry Report for 1885, 1886 (Box 2)
  - Map-Cattle trails from Texas to Kansas Pacific Railroad, undated (Box 2)
  - Newsletter article-"A Turkey Track Trail Herd", 1948 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter,Wyoming Stock Growers Association, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Newsletter, Wyoming Stock Growers Association, 1948 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings-Colorado, etc., 1942-1948 (Box 2)
  - Newspapers-Soundscriber discs of Mark Lane Express, 1876- (Box 2)
  - newspaper-Soundscriber discs of St. Louis Globe Democrat, 1885 (Box 2)
  - Soundscriber disc-British Museum Newspaper Depository, 1946 (Box 2)
  - Soundscriber discs of letters from Wyoming Stock Growers Association files, 1880 (Box 2)
  - Soundscriber discussion of Early Wyoming Cattle Industry, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous notes, 1891 (Box 2)
  - Notes of Swan Co. Livestock Record 1883-1945, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes from Wyoming Stock Growers Association files, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs-Ten Sleep Canyon and unidentified prints, undated (Box 2)
  - Negatives-Ten Sleep Canyon and unidentified prints, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs-Wyoming Cattle Ranchers of English Nobility, 1880-1895 (Box 2)
  - photographs of Swan Ranch and unidentified, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous, 1877-1879 (Box 2)
  - Photographs by Walker of Cheyenne, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs of L7 Cattle Company accounts and unidentified, 1888 (Box 2)
  - Powder River Cattle Co. Memorandum and Articles of Association, 1882-1888 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Debentures and forms of Transfer (not filled out), undated (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Recapitulation of the Three Companies combined, 1882 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Report on the Swan Ranches and Cattle, 1882 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Forms, 1883 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Resolution and Petition, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Resolutions, 1898 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. 33rd Annual Report, 1915 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. 34th Annual Report, 1916 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. 35th Annual Report, etc., 1917 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. 36th Annual Report, etc., 1918 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. 37th Annual Report, etc., 1919 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. 41st Annual Report, etc., 1923 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Report by W.G.L. Winchester, 1924 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Notice of Special Resolution,etc., 1925 (Box 2)
  - Swan Land and Cattle Co. Form for voluntary liquidation., 1926 (Box 2)
  - Photographs-Texas Cattle Pictures, 1904 (Box 2)
  - Photographs-Texas Cattle Pictures, continued, 1904 (Box 2)
  - Photographs-Texas Cattle Pictures, continued, 1904 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-extracts from Buffalo Bulletin, 1891 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-notes from various sources, 1886-1893 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-"Judical Districts of Wyoming", 1865-1937 (Box 2)
  - Johnson Country War-Letter Fred Hesse to Frank Wolcott, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-Letter from Sam Clover, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-poetry from Buffalo Bulletin, 1891 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-letters from Frank Kemp to Fred Hesse, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-Agreement between sheep and cattle men, 1908 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-"A Ballad of the Wyoming 'Rustler War' ", 1947 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-photo of Boise Penrose, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War-reminiscences of A.L. Brock, 1939 (Box 2)
  - transcripts from newspapers regarding Johnson County, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Johnson County War, newsclipping, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs-Bar C herds West of Red Walls, undated (Box 2)
- Series IV. Transportation.
  - Transportation: Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1862 (Box 3)
  - Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1863 (Box 3)
  - Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1864 (Box 3)
  - Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1865 (Box 3)
  - Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1866 (Box 3)
  - Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1867 (Box 3)
  - Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1881-1882, 1885, 1895 (Box 3)
  - New Mexico Toll Roads-notes, 1870 (Box 3)
  - New Mexico Toll Roads, 1882, 1887 (Box 3)
  - Maps of Denver Rio Grande Railway, 1873-1879 (Box 3)
  - News clippings, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Denver Rio Grande and Western Railroad-speeches by Henry Swan, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Denver Rio Grande and Western Rialroad-speeches by Henry Swan, undated (Box 3)
  - Denver Rio Grande and Western Railroad-speeches by Henry Swan, undated (Box 3)
  - Notes on Ouray and Lake Fork Wagon Road Co., undated (Box 3)
  - List of Retired American Life Insurance Companies, undated (Box 3)
  - Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1859 (Box 3)
  - Colorado Toll Roads-notes, 1861 (Box 3)
  - Wagon Roads in Middle Fork, articles of incorporation, 1865-1873 (Box 3)
  - Insurance-speech "Insurance Against the Hazards of Western Life", 1945 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript article on Pliny Fisk Railroad Collection with correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 3)
  - Photograph-unidentified steam engine, undated (Box 3)
  - Speech by J.W. Barriger-"Sir Henry Thornton Pioneer", 1944 (Box 3)
  - Speeches by Brayer "Insurance Against the Hazards of Western Life", 1945 (Box 3)
  - Denver Rio Grande Railroad and W. 1943 Improvement Program, 1942 (Box 3)